Finding Aid for Lewis G. Vander Velde Papers 1855-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lewis G. Vander Velde Papers 1855-1975 1933-1968
Vander Velde, Lewis G. (Lewis George), 1890-1975.
Professor of history and director of Michigan Historical Collections of University of Michigan. Personal and professional correspondence; class notes and lectures; Michigan Historical Commission files; research material on Thomas M. Cooley; material concerning Azazels, University faculty club; letters written as student at University of Michigan, 1912-1913, and at Harvard; and letters written as instructor at Culver Military Academy, and at Teachers' College, St. Cloud, Minnesota in the 1920's; also photographs.
86174 Aa 2 UAm
7.75 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Donor no. 1638
The collection is open for research.
Dr. Lewis G. Vander Velde in addition to being a meticulous scholar and an outstanding teacher was a leader in preserving Michigan's historical heritage. His most well known endeavor was the founding in 1935 of the archival agency later known as the Michigan Historical Collection. The collection's purpose was to increase the attention paid to, and the preservation of, the history of the University of Michigan and the state of Michigan. This accomplishment however was by no means his only effort to create an understanding of and a reverence for local history.
Professor Vander Velde was born in Grandville, Michigan on October 17, 1890. He graduated from Grand Rapids High School in 1908 and enrolled in the solidly Dutch, Hope College in Holland, Michigan. In 1910, he transferred to the University of Michigan. There he received his B.A. in 1913. He taught at Culver Military Academy in Indiana and State Teachers College in St. Cloud, Minnesota. During World War I, he served as a private in the army. In 1921 he received a M.A degree also from the University of Michigan. Harvard awarded him a Ph. D in 1936. His dissertation published by Harvard Historical Studies details the history of the Presbyterian Church during the crisis years of the Civil War.
In 1928, Vander Velde came to the University of Michigan as an instructor in American History. In 1931 he was made assistant Professor, in 1936, he became Associate Professor. He became a full Professor in 1940.
As an historian, American constitutional history was his specialty. His courses in this field were always popular with students, many of whom became leaders in the professions and in public service. He also introduced Michigan History into the curriculum of the History Department at the University of Michigan.
In 1935, Vander Velde received a $700 research grant to collect information relating to the history of Michigan. Three years later the Regents impressed with the growth of his endeavors retitled this project, the Michigan Historical Collections. Dr. Vander Velde was named its first director and held this post until his retirement in 1961. Under his leadership, the Michigan Historical Collections (MHC) developed a fine professional staff, built sound acquisition policies, and acquired materials on the history of the state. These practices established MHC as a clear leader among manuscript and archival agencies in the nation.
In 1951, Dr. Vander Velde was appointed by Governor G. Mennen Williams to the Michigan Historical Commission and he served without interruption until 1974. During his years on the Commission, its staff, publications and total impact on Michigan historical development grew significantly. He was an active member of the board of trustees for the Historical Society of Michigan from 1944 to 1946 and 1956 to 1959 and served as its President in 1958.
Professor Vander Velde was a member of the American Historical Association, the Organization of American Historians and the Society of American Archivists. For many years he collected material on the life and work of Thomas M. Cooley for the purpose of writing a book which was never completed. Dr. Vander Velde died in 1975 in Albion, Michigan.
The papers of Lewis George Vander Velde date from 1855 to 1975 and comprise 7 and 3/4 linear feet of material. The collection is valuable for its documentation of the life of an historian and teacher. Vander Velde papers show a constant attention to, and interest in, Michigan local history. The Collection is arranged into seven series: Biographical Materials; Professional Files; University Class Notes and Lectures; Research Materials (Thomas M. Cooley); Family Papers; Personal Correspondence; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Azazels (University of Michigan); Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Culver Military Academy.; Harvard University.; Historians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Historical Collections.; Michigan Historical Commission.; St. Cloud State College.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; Vander Velde, Lewis G. (Lewis George), 1890-1975.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Children.; Costumes.; Dwellings.; Ranches.; Schools.; Snow.; Soldiers--American.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Students.; Vander Velde, Lewis G. (Lewis George), 1890-1975.; Women.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Materials series contains a scattering of information about Vander Velde's life and career.
  - Memorial tribute, miscellaneous papers relating to personal history (Box 1)
- Professional Files
  The Professional Files series is arranged alphabetically and concerns Vander Velde's activities as director of the Michigan Historical Collections and as historian involved in professional organizations and activities.
  - Unidentified and fragmentary (Box 1)
  - "A" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Adams, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - Aiton, Arthur S (Box 1)
  - American Archivists (Society of) (Box 1)
  - American Association for State and Local History (Box 1)
  - American Historical Association (Box 1)
  - American legion (Box 1)
  - Andrews, Arthur (Box 1)
  - Aukerman, Robert C (Box 1)
  - Automobile Show (National) 1960 (Box 1)
  - Averill, Forrest G (Box 1)
  - Azazels (Faculty and professional club)
    - Historical material (Box 1)
    - Talks (Box 1)
    - Membership material (Box 1)
    - Schedules of meetings, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "B" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Bald, F. Clever (Box 1)
  - Benns, F. Lee (Box 1)
  - Biddle House Restoration project (Box 1)
  - Bigelow, Martha (Box 1)
  - Boak, Arthur E.R (Box 1)
  - Brown, Alan S (Box 1)
  - Brown, Prentiss M (Box 1)
  - Buck, Solon see American Historical Association (Box 1)
  - "C" miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Cargo, Ruth (Box 1)
  - Chapman, Beulah (Box 1)
  - Claver, Willard (Box 1)
  - Clerk's Quarters Building, Mackinac Island (Box 1)
  - College Entrance Requirements, University Committee on 1934 (Box 1)
  - Collier's Year Book 1942-1962 (Box 1)
  - Collier's Special Editor for Michigan (Box 1)
  - Colonial Dames (National Society of) Scholarship (Box 1)
  - Committee on the Combined Curriculum in Letters and Law (Box 1)
  - Committees (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Coulter, Ralph G (Box 1)
  - Cox, W. Howard (Box 1)
  - Crossley, Robert N (Box 1)
  - "D" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Detroit Historical society (Box 1)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts (Box 1)
  - De Vries, Harry (Box 1)
  - Doctoral candidates (General) (Box 1)
  - Doctoral Committees (Box 1)
  - Doll, Louis W (Box 1)
  - Donohue, Francis J (Box 1)
  - Drummond, Donald F (Box 1)
  - Du Bey, Robert E (Box 1)
  - Dunbar, Willis F. (Box 1)
  - Dussenberry, William H (Box 1)
  - Dwelle, Margaret M (Box 1)
  - Dyer, Brainerd (Box 1)
  - "E" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Edelhertz, Herbert (Box 1)
  - Edwardine, Sister Mary (Box 1)
  - Ehrmann, Howard M (Box 1)
  - Ellison, Chester W (Box 1)
  - Ellman, William M (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica Yearbook (Box 1)
  - "F" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Faculty meetings (Box 1)
  - Faculty research funds (Box 1)
  - Fahrner, Jacob Frank, Jr (Box 1)
  - Fielstra, Clarence (Box 1)
  - Fine, Sidney (Box 1)
  - Ford Museum (Box 1)
  - Fort Michelimackinac Restoration (Box 1)
  - Foster, Ruth (Box 1)
  - "G" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Gill, Robert L (Box 1)
  - Ginger, Ann Fagan and Raymond S (Box 1)
  - Graves, Frederick (Box 1)
  - Green, Grace H (Box 1)
  - Gressman, Eugene (Box 1)
  - Gull, Dake (Box 1)
  - "H" miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hansen, Thomas E (Box 1)
  - Hansen, Walter J (Box 1)
  - Harvard University Press (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Mrs. Edna (Box 1)
  - Heideman, Bert M (Box 1)
  - Heitmann, Edmund K (Box 1)
  - Helfman, Harold M (Box 1)
  - Heritage Day (Box 2)
  - Hill, Herbert W (Box 2)
  - Historical Society of Michigan (Box 2)
  - Huang, Ray (Box 2)
  - Hyma, Albert (Box 2)
  - "J" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Jackson, W. Turrentine (Box 2)
  - John, Arthur W (Box 2)
  - Johnson, E. Orville (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Robert G (Box 2)
  - Jones, Alan R (Box 2)
  - K" miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Kennedy, John F (Box 2)
  - King, Dorothy (Box 2)
  - Kitzmiller, Ross J (Box 2)
  - "L" miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Lee, Raymond L (Box 2)
  - Leiter, Forrest (Box 2)
  - Leslie, William R (Box 2)
  - Lewis, Anthony M (Box 2)
  - Lewis, Martin D (Box 2)
  - Lillard family genealogy (Box 2)
  - Laurie, Edward and Nancy (Box 2)
  - "M" miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - "Mc" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Mackey, Frank J (Box 2)
  - Martin, James (Box 2)
  - Mason, Philip (Box 2)
  - May, George S (Box 2)
  - Michigan (Talks and papers about) (Box 2)
  - Michigan Civil War Centennial Commission, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Civil War Religious Committee (Box 2)
  - Michigan Committee on Conservation of Cultural Resources 1941-1944, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Cultural Commission (Box 2)
  - Michigan Historical Collections
    - Speeches about MHC (Box 2)
    - Earhart House as possible home for MHC (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning attempt to obtain the Ford Motor Archives 1958 (Box 2)
    - Buildings needs, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Historical Commission 1954-1960, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Historical Commission (Department of Social Welfare records) (Box 2)
  - Michigan. University of Michigan. Libraries Advisory Committee (Box 2)
  - Michigan. University of Michigan. L.S.A. Centennial Planning Committee 1941 (Box 2)
  - Mississippi Valley Historical Review, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Monteith, John, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "N" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Norton, Clark M (Box 3)
  - Noyes, Edward E (Box 3)
  - "O" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Ohio State University (Box 3)
  - "P" miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Parks, Anne B (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania, Historical Society of (Box 3)
  - Platt, Myles (Box 3)
  - Pollard, Darrell H (Box 3)
  - Prakke, H.J (Box 3)
  - "Presbyterian Churches..." book (Box 3)
  - Presbyterianism (Box 3)
  - Quaife, Milo M (Box 3)
  - "R" miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Radio Talk (D.A.R. talk) January 1936 (Box 3)
  - Registrar's office (Box 3)
  - Religious Education (Box 3)
  - Research Club (Box 3)
  - Research Fund-Division of Social Sciences (Box 3)
  - Retirement messages (Box 3)
  - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Roelofs, Vernon W (Box 3)
  - Rose-Douglas Controversy (notes on) (Box 3)
  - "S" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Seminars, Proseminars & Studies Courses (Committee on) (Box 3)
  - Speech File
    - "Some Unique Aspects of Michigan History" 1949 (Box 3)
    - "Some Unique Omissions in our Federal Constitution" 1956 (Box 3)
    - Mackinac Island History 1957 (Box 3)
    - "The University of Michigan Historical Collections after Twenty Years" 1957 (Box 3)
    - Ben Wheeler Retirement Dinner 1959 (Box 3)
    - Prince Hall Grand Lodge, Niles, Michigan 1960 (Box 3)
  - "U-V-W" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw Historical Society (Box 3)
  - White, J. Patrick (Box 3)
  - Wichers, Willard C (Box 3)
  - Williams, John R (Box 3)
  - Williams (G.M.) papers (Box 3)
  - "X-Y-Z" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Zavala, Silvio (Box 3)
  - Zeleny, Leslie D (Box 3)
- University Class Notes and Lectures
  University Class Notes and Lectures includes notes on various classes, mainly in constitutional history, taught by Vander Velde at the University of Michigan and elsewhere.
  - Bound Book of Essays (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - History 144 (Box 3)
  - History 170 (Box 3)
  - History 173, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - History 174, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - History 176 (Box 4)
  - Reading Lists (Box 4)
  - History 184 (Box 4)
  - History 631-632 (Box 4)
  - Field Course in Michigan History (Box 4)
  - Northwestern University Class Material
    - General (Box 4)
    - History C-16, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - History D-14 (Box 4)
    - History D-18 (Box 4)
- Research Materials (Thomas M. Cooley Biography)
  The Research Materials (Thomas M. Cooley) series consists of research into the life and work of Thomas M. Cooley. Cooley, a law professor at the University of Michigan and a Michigan Supreme Court Judge, served as the first head of the Interstate Commerce Commission. The wide ranging research files collected here encompass but are by no means limited to such materials as hand written letters from Cooley's law students at Michigan, notes on newspaper references to Cooley in the late 1800's, a statistical analysis of Michigan Supreme Court decisions of the same period and the first draft of chapters for a biography of Cooley which was never finished.
  - Bibliography (chronologically arranged) (Box 4)
  - Biography (First draft) (Box 4)
  - Biography (Chapters 1-5) (Box 4)
  - Biography (Chapters 6-9) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with students of TMC (Box 4)
  - Biography (extra pages) (Box 4)
  - Notes and subject files
    - Cooley and the Law School (Box 4)
    - Cooley as Compiler (Box 4)
    - Cooley's Poetry (Box 4)
    - Cooley As Supreme Court Reporter (Box 4)
    - Cooley's Writings (Box 4)
    - Cooley and the Michigan Supreme Court (Box 4)
    - History of Law Department (Box 4)
    - Cooley and the I.C.C (Box 4)
    - Cooley related (Box 4)
    - Speeches-Cooley Fountain (Box 4)
    - Cooley informal talks (Box 4)
    - Azazels Talks (Box 4)
    - Reports on Cooley (Box 4)
    - Cases-carbon copies (Box 4)
    - Cooley's Interest in History-Cooley as an historian (Box 4)
    - T.M.C. Biography (Box 4)
    - Cooley (Box 4)
    - Cooley-Norton (Box 4)
    - Lists for copying (Box 4)
    - Georgiana B. Root (Box 4)
    - Legal Research Sources (Box 4)
    - Baird-Chandler (Box 4)
    - Michaelson (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Suggestions (Box 5)
    - Brief Biographical sketches (Box 5)
    - Seminar topics on Judge Cooley (Box 5)
    - Detroit Free Press on Cooley prepared by Lola Gillam (Box 5)
    - Reference Notebook (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Biographical data (Box 5)
    - Faculty Research Fund (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous items to be checked (Box 5)
    - Assistance (Box 5)
    - Ancestry (Box 5)
    - Biographical Accounts Items re. Early Life (Box 5)
    - Source Citation in Roger's Biography (Box 5)
    - Notes for Biography (Box 5)
    - Notes on Cooley's Diary (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1944 (Box 5)
      includes notes on progress
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous suggestions (Box 5)
    - Burton Historical Collection (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Notes from Michigan Argus (Box 5)
    - Publication Activities of Cooley (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 5)
    - Notes from Watchtower (Box 5)
    - Notes from Michigan Expositor (Box 5)
    - Calendar of Cooley's Letters (Box 5)
    - Law Lectures of Cooley and Campbell at U.M. Law School compiled by David Haughey (Box 5)
    - Statistical Study of Michigan. Supreme Court Cases 1865-1885. Compiled by David Haughey, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Family Papers
  Family papers are arranged chronologically. This series includes some of the earliest of papers in the collection because of Vander Velde's accumulation of letters of family members.
  - 1855-1910, 10 folders (Box 6)
- Personal Correspondence
  Personal Correspondence is a series of exchanges between Vander Velde and various family members and friends.
  - 1912-1915, 48 folders (Box 6)
  - 1916-1934, 89 folders (Box 7)
  - 1935-1968, undated, 85 folders (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous includes photographs and such other items as notebooks, an appointment book, and some notes taken on lectures given by Claude Van Tyne.
  - Postcards (Box 8)
  - Class lecturer notes of Claude Van Tyne 1911 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Notebooks, 3 volumes (Box 8)
  - Appointment book 1929-1930 (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 5 envelopes (Box 8)
    The photographs series includes of students and activities of University of Michigan (1910s and 1920s) and miscellaneous photos.